A Guide to the Susan J. Mellette Papers 1942-1993
Virginia Commonwealth University, Tompkins-McCaw Library
Special Collections and Archives, Tompkins-McCaw Library
Susan J. Mellette Papers, 1942-1993
Special Collections and Archives, Tompkins-McCaw Library
2001/Oct/2
Susan J. Mellette
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for use without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The collection was purchased by the Department from Crown Collectibles in September 2001.
Biographical/Historical Information
Dr. Susan J. Mellette was born on June 4, 1922 in Raleigh, North Carolina and died September 14, 2000. She received her A.B. degree from Merideth College in 1942 followed by her M.D. degree from the University of Cincinnati College of Medecine in 1947. Dr. Mellette's efforts for cancer patients went far beyond just physical issues and help lead to a revolutionary change in cancer patient care nationwide. She was widely regarded as an expert in cancer rehabilitation.
Dr. Mellette joined the MCV faculty in 1955. From 1960-1966 she served as director of MCV's Division of Cancer Studies. She also served on the MCV Admissions Committee for 30 years. Eventually Dr. Mellette would become professor of internal medicine and rehabilitation medicine followed by professor emeritus in 1992. She would retire in 1995.
Dr. Mellette was also involved in various other activities. She served as president of the American Association for Cancer Education. She was involved in various peer review or policy-making committees for the National Cancer Institute. She also ran her own private practice and continued to care for patients up to 1992.
Scope and Content Information
The collection includes correspondence, professional papers, reports, files and published materials dating from 1942 to 1993. The bulk of the collection dates from the 1960s through the 1980s and consists mostly of correspondence and professional papers. The collection focuses on Dr. Mellette's many professional pursuits within the field of oncology.
Arrangement
Arrangement
Materials are arranged alphabetically within each series and chronologically therein.
Organization
Series I-Correspondence (1965-1993, n.d.)
Series II-Professional Papers (1964-1982, n.d.)
Series III-Associations (1971-1987, n.d.)
Series IV-Topics in Cancer (1959-1993, n.d.)
Series V-Miscellaneous
Contents List
- Correspondence, n.d., 1965-1993
  - Cards from Patients 1971-1993 (Box-folder 1.1)
  - Cards from Patients, n.d. (Box-folder 1.2)
  - Department of Health Services 1981, 1984 (Box-folder 1.3)
  - Interoffice, 1966-1970, n.d. (Box-folder 1.4)
  - Interoffice 1971-1984, n.d. (Box-folder 1.5)
  - Louise B. Herndon (1 of 3) (Box-folder 1.6)
  - Louise B. Herndon (2 of 3) (Box-folder 1.7)
  - Louise B. Herndon (3 of 3) (Box-folder 2.1)
  - Miscellaneous 1973, 1984, n.d. (Box-folder 2.2)
  - Office Notes 1978, n.d. (Box-folder 2.3)
  - Outgoing 1972-1973, 1987 (Box-folder 2.4)
  - Personal 1977 (Box-folder 2.5)
  - Professional 1965-1984, n.d. (Box-folder 2.6)
  - The Yellen et al Article Reviewed 1993 (Box-folder 2.7)
- Professional Papers 1964-1982, n.d.
  - Biographical Sketch/Curriculum Vitae, n.d. (Box-folder 2.8)
  - List of New Patients and Prescription Book (Box-folder 2.9)
  - Management of Malignant Disease Metastatic to Bone by Hormonal Alterations by Susan J. Mellete M.D. (Box-folder 2.10)
  - Student admission summary's 1971-1972 (Box-folder 2.11)
  - Notes 1981-1982, n.d. (Box-folder 2.12)
  - Miscellaneous 1981, 1984, n.d. (Box-folder 2.13)
  - Miscellaneous 1964-1973 (Box-folder 2.14)
  - Publications 1973-1981 (Box-folder 2.15)
  - Programs 1971-1983 (Box-folder 2.16)
  - Project Proposal (Intraocular Inflamation: A Non-Pharmacological Approach) (Box-folder 2.17)
  - Receipts: Morton Marks and Sons (Box-folder 2.18)
  - Research and Notes 1965, 1968, 1971, n.d. (Box-folder 2.19)
  - Susan J. Mellette, M.D. Poetic Physician, Foe of Cancer RTD June 9, 1974 (Box-folder 2.20)
  - The Richmond Program for Affordable Health Care February 6, 1984 (Box-folder 2.21)
- Associations 1971-1987, n.d.
  - American Association for Cancer Education 1971, 1973, n.d. (Box-folder 2.22)
  - American Association for Cancer Education: Proposal for Membership (Box-folder 2.24)
  - Cancer Activities Committee (Box-folder 2.24)
  - Friends of the Library 1981-1987 (Box-folder 2.25)
  - New York Academy of Sciences 1971, 1978 (Box-folder 2.26)
  - RES (The 9th National Meeting of the Reticuloendothelial Society) Dec. 5-8, 1972 (Box-folder 2.27)
  - Richmond Academy of Medicine, Inc. (Box-folder 2.28)
- Topics in Cancer 1959-1993, n.d.
  - American Journal of Cardiology January 17, 1989 (Box-folder 3.1)
  - Anticancer and immune suppressive drugs (Box-folder 3.2)
  - Breast Cancer/Chemotherapy: Reports and Teachings on Treatments of Breast Cancer, n.d. 1974-1977 (Box-folder 3.3)
  - Oral Care of the Dying Patient (Box-folder 3.4)
  - Correspondence: Oral Care of the Dying Patient (Box-folder 3.5)
  - Radio Program Transcript: The Crisis of Loss May 26, 1971 (Box-folder 3.6)
  - Time Magazine The New War on Cancer via Virus Research and Chemotherapy July 27, 1959 (Box-folder 3.7)
  - Topics in Clinical Oncology-Breast Carcinoma 1975 (Box-folder 3.8)
- Miscellaneous
  - Copy of Prayer (Box-folder 3.9)
  - Freedom Emblem (Box-folder 3.10)
  - Meredith College (Box-folder 3.11)
  - Newspaper Clippings (Box-folder 3.12)
  - Scrapbook, N.C. Events (Box-folder 3.13)